Betty Hudson Papers GLBTQ.2014.02
GLBTQ Archives
Betty Hudson Papers
1970-2012
GLBTQ.2014.02
GLBTQ Archives
2.0 Linear feet
From 1971-1979, Betty Hudson was a Selectwoman for the Town of Madison, CT and a two-term Democratic State Senator representing Connecticut’s 33rd District. She continued to work for the state in the field of Human Services under Governors Grasso and O’Neill until 1985. This collection includes materials from her endeavors since 1970 including correspondence, articles, and clippings regarding local, state, and national events, community projects, and legislation pertaining to gender and homosexual rights.
Hudson, Betty
Scope and Contents note
This collection contains materials related to gender equality, gay and lesbian civil rights, and state and local government in Connecticut from 1979 to 2012. Related organizations include the Connecticut General Assembly and Human Services Committee, Love Makes a Family, the Permanent Commission on the Status of Women, and the National Organization of Women. Issues discussed consist of local and state legislative issues, use of gender specific titles and language, equal rights for women, and civil rights for gay and lesbian people. The range of materials include correspondence, magazine articles, flyers, reports, and clippings from newspapers such as The Shore Line Times, The Middletown Press, and the New Haven Journal-Courier. Betty Hudson's legislative and political papers were donated to the Connecticut State Library in July 2015.
Biographical/Historical note
Betty Hudson was a Selectwoman for the Town of Madison, CT from 1971-1975, during which time she fought for issues such as improved pension plans and health services, and a town teen center. She successfully led the charge to revise Connecticut’s school bus safety standards. She believed that gender titles should match the gender of the office holder, and worked with State Representative Bill Morris to introduce a bill on the issue. Due in part to her efforts of organizing supporters and testifying in hearings the Gender Title Bill was passed in 1972. In 1974, Ms. Hudson received the Democratic nomination to run for the 33rd District State Senate seat, winning in an overwhelmingly Republican senatorial district and becoming one of the first women elected to the State Senate. As a State Senator from 1975-1979 she served as chairwoman of the Human Services Committee and Human Rights and Opportunities Committee and as a member of the Appropriations Committee, Regulations Review Committee, and Permanent Commission on the Status of Women. In the General Assembly she led the fight for legislation redefining rape as sexual assault, a groundbreaking law that served as a model for other states. Under her guidance, the state passed laws strengthening court-ordered child support with automatic wage attachment, a law requiring police intervention in domestic violence to protect women from retribution, and the establishment of a statewide program of shelters for battered women. She also initiated laws for affirmative action, child day care and Medicaid funding for abortion. In 1975 Ms. Hudson introduced a landmark bill guaranteeing equal rights to gay men and women. The Senate passed the bill, making it the first state legislative chamber to pass such legislation in the United States. Governor Ella Grasso appointed Ms. Hudson as the first Special Assistant for Human Services in 1979. As such, she was the liaison between the Governor’s Office and state Human services departments and agencies such as the Department of Human Resources, Department of Income Maintenance, Department of Children and Youth Services, Department of Mental Health, and many others. She continued in this appointment throughout the terms of Governors Grasso and O’Neill. In 1985 she left the Governor’s Office to work in the Department of Human Resources, first as Executive Assistant to the Commissioner and later as Director of the Bureau of Field Operations. Betty Hudson, who was born in 1931 and has two children, has continued to remain active in local and national organizations such as the National Organization of Women, the Women’s Political Caucus, and the Gay and Lesbian Task Force. She was a strong supporter of the organization “Love Makes a Family,” actively working with them to see the Gay Rights Bill that she introduced in 1975 finally become law in the state of Connecticut in 1991.
Arrangement note
Materials in the collection are arranged chronologically.
Connecticut Women's Rights; Correspondence.; Equal rights ammendments; Feminism.; Gay liberation movement -- Connecticut; Law reform -- Connecticut; Leadership in women -- Connecticut; Marriage law -- Connecticut; Political leadership -- Connecticut; Reproductive health -- Connecticut; Same-sex marriage -- Connecticut; Women -- Connecticut -- Economic conditions; Women -- Connecticut -- History; Women -- Connecticut -- Social conditions; Women -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- Connecticut; Women -- Political activity -- Connecticut; Women politicians -- Connecticut; Women's rights -- Connecticut
- Betty Hudson - donation of legislative and political papers to the Connecticut State Library, July 2015 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- State Senate Inauguration - tickets, stationery, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Connecticut State Senate Race - campaign materials, articles, correspondence, 1972-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Articles about B. Hudson - New York Times, Hartford Times, 1975, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Senator Betty Hudson - press releases, 1976, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1974-1986, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Betty Hudson - contacts, lists (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Prayer in school - Senate debate transcript, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Women and Power Conference - program and remarks by Lee Novick, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Speech given at Wesleyan University re: Connecticut legislation affecting women, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Legislative record and proposals, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Family Life Education Bill (SSB571) - debate excerpts, New London community needs assessment, correspondence, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Governor Ella Grasso - correspondence, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- "The Battered Woman" article by Betty Hudson, Communique Newsletter, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Equal Pay for Equal Work, women's issues - correspondence, bills, fact sheets, articles, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Misc. articles and reports, 1974-1988 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Philip N. Costello, Jr. - articles, correspondence CT Citizen Action Group report, legislative issues, 1971-1978 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Sex Discrimination, Equal Rights - articles, reports, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Speaking engagements - flyers, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Kate Swift/Casey Miller - correspondence, 1972-1996 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Kay Bergin - correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Gender Title Bill (HB8262) - correspondence, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Kate Swift/Casey Miller - correspondence re: gender neutral road signs, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- White House Conference on Families Delegate Selection - correspondence, clippings, candidate bios, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Department of Human Services - living will, power of attorney, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Child Day Care material - article, correspondence, House and Senate Bills, 1979-1990 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- N.O.W - Equal Rights Ammendments, mall decision, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Mystic Oral School issue - article, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Carolyn Gabel - article "An act of civil disobedience", 1990 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Feminist issues, Eleanor Roosevelt - articles, clippings, 1972-1980 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Human Rights and Opportunities public hearings - B. Hudson, chairwoman, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Marilyn Jacobs (legislative intern) - correspondence, evaluations, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Claudia Zanger (legislative intern) - papers, correspondence, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Cindy Kressly (legislative intern) - correspondence, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Margie Kaufman - paper written about B.Hudson, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- CT Women's Political Caucus - Gloria Steinem media release, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Bill to create Department of Human Resources (DHR) - testimony, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- State Senate agenda - lists, agenda, correspondence, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Portland River Boundary BIll - correspondence, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- National Women's Conference - Plan of Action poster, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Jim Abrams (legislative intern) - paper, clippings, correspondence, 1977, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Newspaper columns - Ellen Goodman, Joan Beck, Erma Bombeck, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Reproductive Health Care legislative package - correspondence, fact sheets, bills, notes, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Alan Alda - speech at Connecticut College, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Death of Governor Ella Grasso - correspondence, press release, senate resolution, articles, photograph, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Farmington River flood - articles, 1981-1986 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Senator Audry Beck memorial - correspondence, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Love Makes a Family - flyers, clippings, correspondence, articles, annual reports, 2000-2005 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Opposition to use of tax dollars for programs contrary to pro-life issues - cards (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Clippings, March 1, 1972 - December 29, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Clippings, January 3, 1973 - March 28, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Clippings, April 1, 1974 - March 28, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Clippings, November 6, 1974 - April 10, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Clippings, April 11, 1975 - May 30, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Clippings, June 4, 1975 - December 19, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Clippings, January 1, 1976 - April 29, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Clippings, May 1, 1976 - September 23, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Clippings, September 27, 1976 - November 16, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Clippings, November 26, 1976 - June 30, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Clippings, July 1, 1977 - March 8, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Clippings, March 15, 1978 - October 24, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 10)